Guido Mauricio Mantilla Tarazona

Nearshore Software Development Contractor

Professional experience as a technical leader, digital solutions architect and senior Java developer, with more than 15 years of experience in software development projects, mostly in finance, e-commerce and fintech industries. This has allowed me to have knowledge and experience with many styles, approaches and practices of software architecture and development.

Github: https://github.com/guidomantilla

LinkedIn Profile: https://www.linkedin.com/in/guidomantillatarazona/

HOBBIES

HIIT Training Rock climbing IoT with Arduino Body weight Training Rafting Robotics with Arduino

Heavy weight Training Rapel C/C++ for Arduino

SKILLS

Development Technologies							
Java 8+	Spring Framework	Golang	loT with Arduino	Gradle	Monolith Layered Design		
Java Concurrency Framework	Spring Data	Gin Framework	C/C++ for Arduino	Maven	Monolith Domain Driven Design		
Hibernate JPA	Spring Security	Node.js	Bash Scripts	NPM	REST Architecture Style		
Reflection & Meta Programming	Spring Integration	Express Framework	Git & Github/Gitlab	Sonar	SOA Architecture Style		
Optionals	Spring Shell	Typescript	Veracode	Jenkins	Microservices Architecture Style		
Lambdas & Streams	Spring Boot	Webpack	Fortify	Docker	AWS Architecture		
Cloud Technologies							
AWS S3	AWS Cloudfront	AWS Route53	AWS WAF	AWS API Gateway	AWS ELB		
AWS ECS	AWS Aurora	AWS Storage Gateway	AWS Parameter Store	AWS CloudWatch	AWS VPC		
Databases							
Oracle	Mysql	Mongo	Memcache	Redis	Cassandra		

Soft Skills

Over 4 years of experience leading multidisciplinary teams focused on the creation of value through the development of technological projects. Holistic, strategic, analytical in the identification, analysis and conversion of problems into business opportunities for clients.

Experience with Agile methodologies such as Scrum, Lean Software Development, Design Thinking and Management 3.0

WORK EXPERIENCE

NEARSHORE SOFTWARE DEVELOPMENT CONTRACTOR	BOGOTÁ, COLOMBIA		
Senior Java Developer	(Feb 2020 – To Date)		

As an Nearshore Software Development Contractor, I've been responsible for:

- Adding new features to the current swift-based messaging system.
- Creating a java client for Mailchimp v3 API.
- Integrating Mailchimp Marketing Platform to the current payment gateway.
- Creating a java client for IxoPay v2 API.
- Integrating IxoPay Payment Management Platform to the current payment gateway.

Technologies:

Backend: Java 8, Spring Boot, Docker, Rest, JUnit, Mockito. **CI/CD**: Gradle, Jenkins, Sonar. **AWS**: CloudFront, Route53, WAF, S3, API Gateway, ECS, Aurora, VPC, Elastic Cache, Parameter Store, Cognito. **Architecture**: Java Design Patterns, Service Based Architecture, Services Definition, Services Design Patterns, Domain Driven Design, Migration from Service Based Architectures to Microservices Architectures, Cache Architectural Patterns (Hazelcast and Redis).

ATH S.A / AVAL DIGITAL LABS	BOGOTÁ, COLOMBIA	
Tech Lead / Software Architect	(Mar 2019 – Feb 2020)	

Aval Digital Labs is a company created by financial conglomerate Aval Group to lead the digital transformation for the banks that conform this group.

During this time I participated in the following project:

Project: Popular Bank - Online Saving Account Opening (Mar 2019 - Feb 2020)

The business scope for this project was allowing a lead customer to open a saving account using just browser.

My main responsibilities were:

- Leading the development team and ensuring that the application is designed and developed properly, in compliance with quality standards and architectural guidelines.
- Guiding the project team regarding technological strategies, performing technical feasibility analyses, and defining how to set up all the systems involved.
- Promoting the best software development practices to achieve a better code quality, such as TDD and CI/CD
- Interacting with all the team members to produce functionally and technically complete and correct solutions.
- Working hand-in-hand with the DevOps team to configure all the technical infrastructure and other development tools.
- Designing and implementing single-page applications with Angular 8 and Spring Boot in the backend.
 Following REST architecture and Microservices guidelines in AWS operational contexts, with AWS CloudFront, Route53, WAF, S3, API Gateway, ECS, and Aurora.

Technologies:

Backend: Java 8, Spring Boot, Hazelcast, Docker, Rest, JUnit, Mockito. **FrontEnd**: Angular 8, Karma. **CI/CD**: Gradle, Jenkins, Sonar, Fortify. **AWS**: CloudFront, Route53, WAF, S3, API Gateway, ECS, Aurora, VPC, Elastic Cache, Parameter Store, Cognito. **Architecture**: Java Design Patterns, Service Based Architecture, Services Definition, Services Design Patterns, Domain Driven Design, Migration from Service Based Architectures to Microservices Architectures, Cache Architectural Patterns (Hazelcast and Redis).

BELATRIX
Technical Leader and Java Engineer

BOGOTÁ, COLOMBIA (Jun 2018 – Mar 2019)

Belatrix software is a worldwide leader in software development offshore & nearshore.

During this time I participated in the following project:

• Project: PWC's Budget Expenses Tool (Start date - Last date)

The business scope for this project was allowing a PWC Consultant upload a budget an excel file to an application and make budget analysis easier. This application will parse the excel file (there is no predefined structure for the file), identify the expenses values and their cost center and categories associated.

My main responsibilities were:

- Acting as a liaison between the customer, stakeholders and the development team to ensure that the team focused on the generation of value for them.
- Analyzing, designing and developing software requirements for the application.
- Ensuring that the delivery of the assigned tasks matched the client's quality requirements.
- Developing functionalities and software architectures required by the projects.
- Constantly communicated with the client about the progress and risks of the project requirements. Provided assistance to several areas, such as sales, marketing, and centers of excellence.

Technologies:

Backend: Java 8, Spring Boot, Docker, Rest, JUnit, Mockito, Mongodb. **FrontEnd**: React, Webpack. **CI/CD**: Maven, Jenkins, Sonar, Veracode. **AWS**: CloudFront, Route53, WAF, S3, API Gateway, ECS, Aurora, VPC, Cognito. **Architecture**: Java Design Patterns, Service Based Architecture, Services Definition, Services Design Patterns, Domain Driven Design.

STEFANINI
Software Architect and Technical Leader

CALI, COLOMBIA (Jan 2017– Mar 2018)

Stefanini is a worldwide leader in software development consultancy and development.

During this time I participated in the following projects:

• Purchase Portal (Jan 2017- Mar 2018)

Write a brief overview about the project.

Main tasks executed in the project:

- Leading the definition of software architectures for the Coomeva Business Group.
- Complying with the defined standards and methodologies and took into consideration the risks and restrictions in the environments where these systems would operate.
- Evaluating and adopting new technologies and architectural styles that added value to the business.
- Ensured the application of architecture at each stage of the project.
- Designed and implemented single-page applications with Angular 5 and Spring Boot, Laravel and Node.js in the backend.

Technologies:

Backend: Java 8, Spring Boot, Rest, JUnit, Mockito, Nodejs, Expressjs, Laravel, Mongodb, Oracle. **FrontEnd**: Angular 5, Karma. **CI/CD**: Maven, NPM, Composer, Jenkins, Sonar. **Architecture**: Java Design Patterns, Service Oriented Architecture, Services Definition, Services Design Patterns.

> CALI, COLOMBIA (May 2013 – Dec 2016)

PRAGMA SOA Architect and Technical Leader

Pragma is a Colombian leader in software development consultancy and development.

During this time I participated in several projects having different roles: Developer, Senior Developer, Software Architect and Branch Technical Leader.

Main tasks executed in the projects:

- Technical Leadership for 25 developers.
- Acting as a liaison between the customers and the development team to ensure that the team focused on the generation of value for them.
- Coordinating and supporting Agile inception technique at the beginning of each project. Defined the SOA and BPM architectures of the projects.
- Coordinating the definition of the functional and non-functional scope of the projects. Managed the projects and sprint time estimations.
- Assigning development teams to each client.
- Leading and coordinating the development teams.
- Ensuring the compliance with the Agile Pragma methodology.
- Assessing project impediments.

- Defining training plans for the development teams.
- Designing the architecture of software solutions implemented ..
- Ensuring that the new applications complied with the architectural guidelines. Coordinated work teams in all phases of the project.
- Providing expertise in Java EE, Spring Framework, Maven, SonarQube, IBM WebSphere Application Server, JUnit, Jenkins, IBM Business Process Manager, and IBM Integration Bus.
- Providing support to the technical definition of SOA and BPM architectures and their implementation by means of IBM Business Process Manager and IBM Integration Bus.

Technologies:

Backend: Java 8, Spring Boot, Rest, JUnit, Mockito, IBM WebSphere Application Server, IBM Business Process Manager, IBM Integration Bus, Oracle. **FrontEnd**: Angular 5, Karma. **CI/CD**: Maven, NPM, Composer, Jenkins, Sonar. **Architecture**: Java Design Patterns, Service Oriented Architecture, Services Definition, Services Design Patterns.

EDUCATION

Jun 2001 – Jul 2006	Bachelor's Degree in Systems Engineering	Universidad Autónoma de Bucaramanga
Jun 2015 – Jul 2017	Specialization in Processes for Software Development	Universidad San Buenaventura
Jun 2018 – Jul 2018	Diploma in Innovation Training	Universidad ICESI
2013	Agile Methodologies for Software Development Project Management	Universidad Tecnológica Nacional de Buenos Aires
2013	IBM Certified SOA Solution Designer [2007]	IBM
2013	IBM Certified SOA Associate [2008]	IBM
2015	Seminar on Applied Software Architecture in SOA Contexts and Cloud Computing	Universidad ICESI
2016	Certified SOA Professional	Arcitura Education Inc.

2016	Management Workout	3.0	+	Happy Melly One
2018	Amazon Web S Architect & Deve		; -	UDEMY